University of Connecticut 1987.0011
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
University of Connecticut, President's Office Records [John A. DiBiaggio, 1979-1985]
undated, 1952-1986
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1987.0011
36.75 Linear Feet
In March, 1979, John A. DiBiaggio became the tenth president of the University of Connecticut, eleven months after the resignation of Glenn W. Ferguson.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The files were transferred in three separate accessions. Files dated circa 1979-1981 were transferred in 1985, files to 1985 were transferred in 1987 and the speeches were transferred in 1988.
Arrangement
Series I: Inauguration (1979) pertains to the planning and execution of the inauguration ceremony for President DiBiaggio held on 8 September 1979. The records include planning documents from the Inauguration Committee, invitation lists, the program, newspaper clippings, and formal letters of congratulations to President DiBiaggio from various colleges and universities. This series is arranged alphabetically by folder heading
Series II: Administration (1974-1985 [bulk, 1979-1985]) provides information on the university administration activities of the President's office during President John DiBiaggio's tenure. The files contain correspondence between the president's office and campus schools, colleges, departments, offices, institutes, centers, faculty committee, branch campuses, and trustees; as well as correspondence relating to university-sponsored programs and activities. There are memoranda, reports, newsletters, and some committee minutes. Subjects and correspondents include the Alumni Association, athletics, collective bargaining, the Computer Center, Exchange programs, finance and Administration, the Health Center, the Office for Affirmative Action, the Office of Institutional Research, Student Affairs and Services, University of Connecticut Educational Properties, Inc., and the UConn Foundation. There are particular topics of interest such as women in athletics and Title IX, cults on campus, gay rights, racial relations, pornography, sexual harassment, and U.S.D.A. animal care violations. The series is arranged alphabetically by folder heading.
Series III: State Government (undated, 1952-1986 [bulk, 1980-1983]) contains correspondence between the office of President DiBiaggio and state governmental offices, boards, bureaus, departments, commissions, and state legislative and regulatory bodies, as well as state representatives and the Connecticut General Assembly. Specific correspondents include the Board of Regents, the Board of Higher Education, and governor's Advisory Committees. Subjects include legislative inquires and the restructuring of public higher education. This series is arranged alphabetically by folder heading.
Series IV: Federal Government (undated, 1973-1986 [bulk, 1975-1983]) contains correspondence between the President's Office and Connecticut congressional representatives and senators, federal governmental departments, commissions and bureaus, as well as branches of the armed forces. The correspondents include Senator Christopher Dodd; Congresspersons Stewart B. McKinney, Toby A. Moffet, Lawrence J. Denardis, and Barbara Kennelly; State department; the Departments of Education, and Health, Education, and Welfare; the National Science Foundation; the U.S. Postal Service; and the Veterans Administration. Special items include information on Tax Relief Act $.311 (pertaining to college education), the Equal Rights Amendment, the Education Appropriations Bill, and Section 504 (pertaining to the handicapped). The series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent or topic.
Series V: Educational Associations (1973-1984 [bulk, 1979-1984]) contains correspondence between President DiBiaggio's office and various regional and national associations such as the American Council on Education, the Council for Advancement and Support of Education, and the National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges. In addition to correspondence, the series includes some printed materials such as newsletters, reports, and informational brochures from the associations. The series is arranged alphabetically by association, and, within each subject heading, chronologically.
Series VI: Subject Files (1974-1986 [bulk, 1976-1983]) contains correspondence between the office of President DiBiaggio and various corporations, foundations, individuals, and community groups, as well as correspondence with local Chambers of Commerce, town governments, and various media. The files contain correspondence and information on specific subjects and events such as Nuclear Arms Week and the Atlanta Crisis. The series is arranged alphabetically by folder heading.
Series VII: Speeches (undated, 1977-1985 [bulk, 1979-1985]) contains President DiBiaggio's speeches, as well as addresses and messages to the University administration, faculty, and students; state and federal legislatures; government agencies; and local, state, and national professional and business groups. Included are commencement and convocation addresses delivered at both the University of Connecticut and other colleges and universities, television and newspaper editorials by president DiBiaggio, presentations at award ceremonies, testimonials and dedications, and testimony before various state and federal legislative committees. Speeches address topics such as the future of American education, the state of health and dental care in the United States, Black and Hispanic history, and the Centennial of the University of Connecticut>. The series is arranged in reverse chronological order by date of the speech.
History
In March 1979, John A. DiBiaggio became the tenth president of the University of Connecticut, eleven months after the resignation of Glenn W. Ferguson. DiBiaggio began his tenure as president at a time when the University was faced with a number of difficult problems; state funding was inadequate, morale was low within the University community, and there were concerns about the effectiveness of affirmative action programs in employment and enrollment. DiBiaggio worked to address all these problems.
Due to regional economic problems and legislative indifferences, state, support for the University had declined during the 1970s. DiBiaggio was committed to reversing this trend. By 1982, funding was stabilized both by an improving economy and DiBiaggio's capable articulation to the legislature of the Universities needs. The University gained additional support with the establishment of the Tuition Fund, which allowed it to retain tuition payments, as well as through the Second Century Capital Campaign, the first major fund raising campaign in the school's history. The UConn Foundation directed this campaign, which by 1985 had raised almost $25 million from the corporate and University communities. Its immense success was due, in part, to DiBiaggio's amiable relations with Connecticut's corporate community.
DiBiaggio strove to improve morale among both the students, and faculty. Throughout his presidency he remained accessible to students and student leaders. Students found him charismatic and likeable. Faculty admired his commitment to maintenance of academic standards. During his presidency, an Academic Master Plan, Opportunities for the 80's, was developed outlining the University's efforts toward academic excellence. Additional long-range plans were created for the student support services, research and graduate studies, the Health Center in Farmington, mainframe computer utilization, and facilities planning and renovation. The most ambitious plan in the DiBiaggio years was one to establish a research park and convention center, the Connecticut Technology Park, on 350 acres north of the Storrs campus.
In addition to the celebration of the University's centennial in 1981, several notable accomplishments were achieved during the DiBiaggio presidency. In September 1984, the Law School moved to a new location at the twenty-acre site at the former Hartford Seminary Foundation. One month later, the Avery Point campus was designated the undersea research center for the coastal northeast and the Great Lakes states. The Marine Sciences Institute was financed by a $1 million grant from the federal maritime program of National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Association.
Despite its many gains, the University suffered setbacks and disappointments during these years. In 1983, the Board of Governors of Higher Education voted to close the Torrington Branch of the University in the face of perennial low enrollments. The University's affirmative action program saw only limited success despite president DiBiaggio's efforts. In 1979, minority enrollment throughout the University's system numbered only 1.313, or about 6% of the student population; by 1984, this total had increased to only 1,654, or about 7% of the student population. DiBiaggio's dream to elevate the University of Connecticut from among the country's top sixty research universities tone of its top twenty was not realized. The overall image of the university both within the states and across the country did improve, however, under DiBiaggio's leadership. As a reporter for the Hartford Courant said, "During his five and a half years as president of the University of Connecticut, John DiBiaggio helped to put the school back on the map."
The university experienced only moderate growth in most areas during the DiBiaggio years. In Fall 1979, there were 12,842 undergraduate and graduate students enrolled on the Storrs campus who were Connecticut residents, and 1,963 who were non-residents. It cost the average Connecticut undergraduate approximately $3,700 to attend the university for one year: $1,048 in tuition and fees, $1,525 for room and board, and about $1,127 for books and personal expenses. 4,629 degrees were conferred; of which 3,072 were bachelor's degrees. There were 4,491 full-time employees: 1,994 women, and 2,497 men. There were 1,246 faculty, University Library had 1,278,884 volumes. The physical plant had 447 usable structures on the Storrs campus. The University budget was approximately $130,153,661.
In Fall 1984, there were 12,994 undergraduate and graduate students enrolled on the Storrs campus who were Connecticut residents, and 2,346 who were non-residents. It cost the average Connecticut undergraduate approximately $1,657 in tuition and fees, and $2,362 for room and board to attend the university for one year. 4,326 degrees were conferred; of which 2,825 were bachelor's degrees. There were 1,205 faculty, 1,674 classified, 447 graduate assistants, and 1,035 other professionals. The University Library had 1,489,127 volumes. The physical plant had 448 useable structures on the Storrs campus, with a total of 4,047,490 assignable square feet of floor space. The University budget was approximately $203,869,000.
DiBiaggio, born in 1932 in San Antonio, Texas, was raised in Detroit, Michigan. He was the son of Italian immigrants and was the first member of his family to attend college. He received his bachelor's degree from Eastern Michigan University in 1954. He received his dental degree in 1958 from the University of Detroit School of Dentistry, and, in 1967, earned a master's degree in university administration from the University of Michigan.
From 1958 to 1965, he practiced general dentistry in New Baltimore, Michigan and taught part-time at the University of Detroit Dental School. From 1967 to 1976, he held both administrative and teaching positions at the University of Kentucky and Virginia Dental School in 1970 at the age of 37. He came to the University of Connecticut in 1976 as Vice-President for Health Affairs and Executive Director of the John Dempsey Health Center in Farmington. He is married to Carolyn DiBiaggio. The DiBiaggios have three children: David, Dana, and Deirdre. John A. DiBiaggio resigned as president June 1985 to accept the presidency of Michigan State University.
Scope and Content
The collection contains the office files created during DiBiaggio's tenure as President of the University of Connecticut> from 1979 through 1985. Included in the collection is correspondence, reports, minutes, memoranda, newspaper clippings, reports and publications. See Arrangement for details on the issues covered by the collection.
Correspondence; Photographs; Press releases; Administrative records; Financial Records; Photocopies; Notes; Monographs; Connecticut (state); Newspapers; Affirmative action programs in education; Speeches (documents); Newsletters; College administrators; Universities and colleges; College presidents; University of Connecticut. President's Office; University of Connecticut; University of Connecticut. President's Office
- Series I: Inauguration, undated, 1979
  - Cazel, Fred A., undated (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Inauguration Committee, 1979 (Box 1:, Folder 2-7)
  - Inauguration Committee, 1979 (Box 2:, Folder 8-9)
  - Congratulatory letters and certificates from colleges and Universities, 1979
    - Alcorn State University (Box 2:, Folder 10)
    - Columbia University (Box 2:, Folder 11)
    - Georgia Institute of Technology (Box 2:, Folder 12)
    - Indiana University (Box 2:, Folder 13)
    - Louisiana State University (Box 2:, Folder 14)
    - Princeton University (Box 2:, Folder 15)
    - Purdue University (Box 2:, Folder 16)
    - University of Hartford (Box 2:, Folder 17)
    - University of Mississippi (Box 2:, Folder 18)
    - University of Oklahoma (Box 3:, Folder 19)
    - Vanderbilt University (Box 3:, Folder 20)
  - Invitation list, 1979 (Box 3:, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1979 (Box 3:, Folder 22)
  - Inauguration speech: Gordon W. Tasker, 1979 (Box 3:, Folder 23)
  - Luncheon Program, 1979 (Box 3:, Folder 24)
  - Congratulatory certificates, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Dartmouth College
    - Harvard University
    - United States Military Academy
- Series II: Administration, 1974-1985; 1979-1985
  - A, 1984 (Box 5:, Folder 25)
  - Academic Affairs, 1979-1984 (Box 5:, Folder 26-28)
  - Academic Affairs: vice president search, 1980 December - 1981 August (Box 5:, Folder 29)
  - Academic calendar, 1979 September - 1980 May (Box 5:, Folder 30)
  - Academic planning, 1983 April (Box 5:, Folder 31)
  - Activities office, 1979-1981 (Box 5:, Folder 32)
  - Administrative review, 1980 August - 1981 July (Box 5:, Folder 33)
  - Admissions, 1979-1983 (Box 5:, Folder 34-35)
    - Inquiries, 1980-1984 (Box 5:, Folder 36-38)
    - Reports, 1984 (Box 5:, Folder 39-40)
    - Transfer policy, 1974-1981 (Box 5:, Folder 41)
  - Affirmative Action [See: Office of Affirmative Action]
  - Afro-American Cultural Center, 1979-1982 (Box 5:, Folder 42-43)
  - Alcohol policy, 1980-1983 (Box 5:, Folder 44-45)
  - Allied Health, 1979-1983 (Box 5:, Folder 46-48)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha, 1980-1983 (Box 5:, Folder 49)
  - Alumni Association
    - Alumni Association, 1979 February - December (Box 5:, Folder 50)
    - Board of Directors & Alumni Council, 1979-1981 (Box 5:, Folder 51)
    - Distinguished Professor Award, 1979 March (Box 5:, Folder 52)
    - Faculty Award for excellence, 1979-1980 (Box 5:, Folder 53)
    - Miscellaneous, 1979-1985 (Box 5:, Folder 54-57)
    - President's Contingency Fund, 1980-1984 (Box 5:, Folder 58-61)
    - Representation Allowances, 1979-1984 (Box 6:, Folder 62-64)
    - Society of 1881, 1975-1977 (Box 6:, Folder 65)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1979 January - June (Box 6:, Folder 66)
    Scope and Contents note
    [See also: Collective bargaining]
  - Animal care center, 1980 July - 1981 April (Box 6:, Folder 67)
  - Animal Reports, 1980-1983 (Box 6:, Folder 68-69)
  - Associated Student Commissaries, 1979-1982 (Box 6:, Folder 70-71)
  - Associated Student Government, 1975-1979 (Box 6:, Folder 72)
  - Athletics, 1979-1984 (Box 6:, Folder 73-75)
    - Academic coordinator, 1982-1983 (Box 6:, Folder 76)
    - Advisory Committee, 1975-1983 (Box 6:, Folder 77-78)
    - Big East Conference, 1979-1983 (Box 6:, Folder 79-81)
    - Complimentary tickets policy, 1982-1983 (Box 6:, Folder 82)
    - Intercollegiate sports cuts, 1980 August - 1981 March (Box 6:, Folder 83-84)
    - Multi-purpose facility, 1978-1983 (Box 6:, Folder 85-86)
    - N.C.A.A., 1979-1984 (Box 6:, Folder 87-93)
    - Title IX, 1980-1984 (Box 6:, Folder 94-97)
    - UConn Club, 1979 January (Box 7:, Folder 98)
    - Women in Athletics: Ethics and Eligibility Committee, 1978-1981 (Box 7:, Folder 99-102)
    - Women/N.C.A.A., 1980 December 12 (Box 7:, Folder 103)
    - Yankee Conference, 1979-1984 (Box 7:, Folder 104-106)
  - Attorney, 1980-1984 (Box 7:, Folder 107-109)
  - Avery Point Branch [See: Southeastern Branch]
  - B, 1984 (Box 7:, Folder 110)
  - Ballroom Dance Club, 1980 (Box 7:, Folder 111)
  - Barney House, 1979-1983 (Box 7:, Folder 112)
  - Beach, Charles Foundation, 1980-1981 (Box 7:, Folder 113)
  - Big East Conference [See: Athletics—Big East Conference]
  - Bio-behavioral sciences, 1979-1984 (Box 7:, Folder 114-116)
  - Biological Sciences, 1979-1983 (Box 7:, Folder 117-118)
  - Bloodmobile, 1979-1984 (Box 7:, Folder 119)
  - Board of Governors, 1982 (Box 7:, Folder 120)
  - Board of Trustees
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Planning, 1982 (Box 7:, Folder 121)
    - Community Relations Committee, 1980 January (Box 7:, Folder 122)
    - Long Range Planning Committee, 1977-1980 (Box 7:, Folder 123)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978-1983 (Box 7:, Folder 124-127)
  - Branch [Campuses], 1979-1980 (Box 7:, Folder 128)
    [See also: Hartford Branch, Southeastern Branch, Stamford Branch, Torrington Branch, Waterbury Branch]
  - Branch faculty status: salary, 1979-1981 (Box 7:, Folder 129)
  - Branford House, 1985 (Box 7:, Folder 130)
  - Breakfast, monthly, 1982-1983 (Box 7:, Folder 131)
  - Brundage Pool: asbestos ceiling allegations, 1981 (Box 7:, Folder 132)
  - Budget, 1983, 1985 (Box 7:, Folder 133)
  - Building Names Committee, 1977-1981, 1983 (Box 7:, Folder 134-135)
  - Burke, Fred, 1982-1983 (Box 7:, Folder 136)
  - Bursars Office, 1978-1984 (Box 7:, Folder 137-138)
  - By-laws, 1979-1981 (Box 7:, Folder 139)
  - C, 1983-1984 (Box 7:, Folder 140)
  - Cabinet; reporting relationships, 1979-1980 (Box 7:, Folder 141)
  - Cabinet retreat, 1984 (Box 7:, Folder 142-143)
  - Capital campaign corporate contracts, 1981-1983 (Box 7:, Folder 144)
  - Capital campaign dinner Centennial, 1982 (Box 7:, Folder 145)
    - Capital campaign, 1979 November - 1980 April (Box 7:, Folder 146)
    - Miscellaneous, 1977-1980 (Box 7:, Folder 147)
    - Coordinating Committee, 1978-1980 (Box 7:, Folder 148)
  - Center for Black Studies, 1979-1982 (Box 7:, Folder 149-150)
  - Center for a Greater University, 1982 (Box 7:, Folder 151)
  - Center for Human Resources [See: School of Social Work]
  - Center for Instructional Media and Technology, 1982 (Box 7:, Folder 152)
  - Center for Italian Studies, 1976 February (Box 7:, Folder 153)
  - Center for Latin American Studies, 1978, 1980-1981 (Box 7:, Folder 154)
  - Center for Personal Growth, 1979 May - November (Box 7:, Folder 155)
  - Center for Real Estate Urban Economic Studies, 1975-1980 (Box 7:, Folder 156)
  - Center for Slavic & East European Studies, 1979-1981 (Box 7:, Folder 157-158)
  - Chemical Engineering Industrial Advisory Board, 1978-1983 (Box 8:, Folder 159-160)
  - Collective bargaining, 1978-1981 (Box 8:, Folder 161)
    - American Association of University Professors (AAUP), 1978-1983 (Box 8:, Folder 162-166)
    - Bill # 7832, 1979 January - April (Box 8:, Folder 167)
    - Classified staff, 1979 May - November (Box 8:, Folder 168)
    - Classified staff and clerical, 1982-1983 (Box 8:, Folder 169)
    - E.O. Smith High School, 1976-1981 (Box 8:, Folder 170-171)
    - Health Center, 1978-1982 (Box 8:, Folder 172)
    - Independent, 1982 (Box 8:, Folder 173)
    - Miscellaneous, 1979-1983 (Box 8:, Folder 174-175)
    - University of Connecticut Professional Employees Association (UCPEA), 1979-1983 (Box 8:, Folder 176-177)
  - College of Agriculture and Natural Resources, 1979-1983 (Box 8:, Folder 178-181)
    - Ratcliffe Hicks, 1979 February (Box 8:, Folder 182)
  - College of Liberal Arts and Sciences, 1979-1983 (Box 8:, Folder 183-185)
  - Combustion Engineering Training Center Corp., 1982 (Box 8:, Folder 186)
  - Commencement: Law School, 1978, 1979 (Box 8:, Folder 187)
  - Committee on violence Against Women, 1981-1983 (Box 8:, Folder 188-190)
  - Computer Center, 1979-1984 (Box 8:, Folder 191-193)
    - Caster, Robert issue, 1982 (Box 8:, Folder 194)
    - Equipment loss, 1983-1984 (Box 8:, Folder 195)
  - Conference Room Committee, 1982 October 25 (Box 8:, Folder 196)
  - Connecticut Daily Campus, 1979-1984 (Box 8:, Folder 197-198)
  - Connecticut Public Interest Research Group, 1980 (Box 8:, Folder 199)
  - Consulting policy, 1979-1980 (Box 9:, Folder 200)
  - Contributions, 1981 March (Box 9:, Folder 201)
  - Comptroller, 1974-1981 (Box 9:, Folder 202)
  - Co-Op, 1979-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 203-204)
  - Cooperative Education, 1979-1981 (Box 9:, Folder 205)
  - Council on Human Rights and Opportunities, 1977-1984 (Box 9:, Folder 206-210)
  - Counseling and Testing Center, 1975-1979 (Box 9:, Folder 211)
  - Cults on campus, 1979-1981 (Box 9:, Folder 212)
  - Day of Metanoia, 1979 (Box 9:, Folder 213)
  - Day of Pride [See: Student Affairs and Services]
  - Delta Sigma Phi, 1982 April 20 (Box 9:, Folder 214)
  - Department of Anthropology, 1981, 1983 (Box 9:, Folder 215)
  - Department of Art, 1983 (Box 9:, Folder 216)
  - Department of Chemistry, 1979-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 217-218)
  - Department of Communication Sciences, 1976-1981 (Box 9:, Folder 219)
  - Department of Dramatic Arts, 1979-1981 (Box 9:, Folder 220)
  - Department of Economics, 1976-1981 (Box 9:, Folder 221)
  - Department of English, 1979-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 222-223)
  - Department of Foreign Languages, 1980 (Box 9:, Folder 224)
  - Department of History, 1976-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 225-226)
  - Department of Journalism, 1976-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 227)
  - Department of Linguistics, 1981 (Box 9:, Folder 228)
  - Department of Mathematics, 1979, 1981 (Box 9:, Folder 229)
  - Department of Music, 1976-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 230-231)
  - Department of Nutritional Studies, 1975, 1979 (Box 9:, Folder 232)
  - Department of Philosophy, 1977-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 233-234)
  - Department of Physics, 1979-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 235-236)
  - Department of Political Sciences, 1979-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 237-238)
  - Department of Psychology, 1979-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 239-241)
  - Department of Romance and Classical Languages, 1979-1982 (Box 9:, Folder 242-243)
    [See also: Foreign Languages]
  - Department of Sociology, 1980-1981 (Box 9:, Folder 244)
  - Department of Statistics, 1976-1977, 1979 (Box 9:, Folder 245)
  - Development, 1980 (Box 9:, Folder 246)
  - Development Office, 1978-1982 (Box 9:, Folder 247-250)
  - Development search: Director, 1980 February - July (Box 9:, Folder 251)
  - Distinguished Professor Award [See: Alumni Association]
  - Donations, 1979-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 252-253)
  - Donations: Michaels's Jewelers, 1980 August - November (Box 9:, Folder 254)
  - E, 1983-1984 (Box 9:, Folder 255)
  - E.O. Smith High School, 1979-1983 (Box 9:, Folder 256-257)
  - Education, School of [See: School of Education]
  - Educational records inventory, 1980 June 30 (Box 9:, Folder 258)
  - Emeritus faculty, 1979-1981 (Box 9:, Folder 259)
  - Energy conservation, 1978-1980 (Box 10:, Folder 260-261)
  - Engineering, School of [See: School of Engineering]
  - Enrollments, 1982-1984 (Box 10:, Folder 262)
  - Exchange Program